so when a person begins
of renunciation
and they they hear that uh you know
sensual pleasures are bad therefore therefore
every
pleasure any pleasure that it's experienced
any pleasure that it's experienced
it's bad
yeah if it's experienced to the eye
there's a medical site there's no
there's no discernment of difference in
the type of pleasure
in the beginning
it's like that similar debates with them
from aji nikaya
that first you know they debate that
they engage with central pleasures
unrarely then the second herd realizes the danger
then the second herd realizes the danger
of it and then says no to all of it
and then stops and then goes back and
eats debate again
so it's very similar when a person hears
or sensory strain centrality is bad
then automatically naturally
the mind just goes into the mode of our
case so any sense of pleasure
of any kind
any agreeability
any comfort is bad thus i might say no
to
and that's that's unsustainable
and ignoble
because now you're overly denying things
sensuality is overly affirming
taking the bait not just the food
and um denying it so and then saying no
to everything like that it's basically
denying overly denying it
so dismissing the food
because of the bait
all food all food because of the bait
yeah all signs
all signs
all sights sound smell test touches all
of it
and and that's that's like what buddha
himself realizes like wait
why am i afraid of the pleasures
that have nothing to do
with sensuality with central types of
pleasures so what if i what if i were not to be
so what if i what if i were not to be
afraid and then he wasn't and then you
realize okay now this is how you abandon
sociality not just to hold on to a view
that any pleasure through senses is
central pleasure thus i can't help it
thus i'm justified in engaging with
i'm justified in engaging with
sensuality or i'm justified in shunning
the whole things and denying everything
there is nothing in between
no there is a lot in between and that's
the whole point so in the beginning you
might have to end up restraining
overly saying no to
saying no to
things that you don't necessarily
say no to the work is to discern what
type of pleasure is the pleasure of
sensuality what type of pleasure
what type of pleasure
uh in relation to the senses is central
pleasure and what type of pleasure in
relation to the senses is not central
because for as long as you live you will
have the senses
yes side sound smell these touches so
that's unavoidable
so it's only a particular
type of pleasure that is unwholesome
that is what comes under what we call
sensuality there must be abandoned cut
off with the root and that whole thing
you'll never see that if you're refusing
to stop dismissing the entire thing or
you'll never see that if you refuse to
stop saying yes to the entire thing
um so in the buddha they describe in the
suttas he said so what is what are the
five chords of the central pleasure
he didn't say any sight sounds maltese
touch that you find agreeable
he said the science and smell test
dodgers that you find agreeable that are
um
inducing lust they're provocative of
lust or favor of thirst
and you already know what those things
are you know admiring a beautiful sunset be
you know admiring a beautiful sunset be
up with that sensuality it's not
that is agreeable sight but will your
mind be feverish with with sexual lust
and thirst and or glutton on a kind of a
something hungry hunger on a kind of
something inconceivable
inconceivable
would you be able to not sleep because
you know you're so dependent on seeing
sunsets or something or sitting in the
forest no it's inconceivable so there is
a difference there
and that's the whole point
you have to kind of
resist like trying to dismiss the whole
thing because it feels honest everything
is bad or everything is fine
and actually learn how to eat around the
bait and not take the bait
and that's that you know all the
previous talks we're doing about you
know knowing where your motivation is
rooted in the reason for your action
but all that all of that can help you to
realize okay so you kind of already
recognize the intention that is aimed at
that type of pleasure that is
provocative of last even indirectly so
you would start seeing more things that
are related to that type of pleasure and
being able to be more even more accurate
in avoiding that and then cultivating
pleasures that have nothing to do with
sensuality such as pleasure of seclusion
pleasure of remote dwellings that are
far from actually physically pleasant or
inducing of lust or something like that
but they're actually they become they
become very agreeable
so for example
uh for example
food you can eat food which
you can eat food which
makes you even more hungry you know yeah
certain fast food exactly exactly you
have to eat so that's like the type of
sensuality that it's sort of like initially
that it's sort of like initially
everything every food essential
uh
but that is unavoidable so you would
have to eat so what do you do to just
then eat completely that
without any regard
or do you make the effort to discern
reasons for eating and that whole right
contemplation this is healthy exactly so
then you would you would start seeing
that oh no yeah there's a food that you
know i find agreeable but i don't
necessarily fantasize about think about
plants spend hours of trying to get it
would be upset if i don't get it also
there is fever involved involved there
like there's this proper dependence on
experiencing a particular type of
pleasure through the senses
so okay so i won't go for that food but
if i have other food i don't need to eat
food that makes me disgusted and gagging
i want to vomit or something that's
equally ridiculous the food that fills
me up exactly for me that's a pleasure
health find a find a purpose so that's
agreeable but it's not something that
will obsess your mind and provoke lust
in it for more and so on
so so that's pretty much it it's quite
an easy criteria or like you know i want
to go out and stuff why
you ask yourself what's the purpose ah
company friends carelessness
distractions all of these things will
result in provocation of lust aversion
indolence distraction so you know it
will be it will end in seeking
unwholesome pleasures
well i want to go out because i'll just
go on a quiet walk or something in a
very agreeable park
that's not sensuality that's
agreeability and actually you if you start discerning
and actually you if you start discerning
that the clearer it becomes you can you
can more like basically completely
divert your actions even your mind from wanting
your actions even your mind from wanting
to go into sensuality and just find
things that are agreeable of non lustful
provocative kind of fever and thirst but
for example those monks they will go and
live in the forests
you know like when the buddha said
even if a monk goes to forest and his
mind is just full of sensual thoughts
and he's just sleeping
and not doing anything he's in the
environment that is not
that is not
uh environment of the five chords of
central pleasures beautiful forest it's
not it's not provocative of lust it's
not provocative
so his mind will quiet down
and he'll settle in and then he'll start
benefiting from that environment
the other type of monk who is not
his mind is not full of lust he's not
sleepy he's diligent but he lives in the
middle of the village
well his mind will become basically
provoked with lust and everything else
because he lives in the environment that
is filled with his five chords of
sensual pleasure
he will be provoked he will be provoked
sooner or later
so so you know you recognize that you
use this type of pleasure of seclusion
or renunciation
uh to to overcome dependence of this
particular provocative type of pleasure
of senses which is what centrality is
and then later on sure you can develop
even further of your samadhi and then
completely surmount any dependence on
any agreeability of the senses but as
long as you have the senses
till the body breaks apart agreeably
disagreeable will be coming your way
but obviously you will neither be uh you
know acting with lust towards agreeable
or acting with the virgin to us disagree
if the mind is already developed to that
point so so it's it it is actually quite
so so it's it it is actually quite
important because like even many monks
would just fall into that trap you know
you take on winner rules precepts and
then just no oh no oh no no for
everything and and then you're just doubling down
and and then you're just doubling down
and saying no to everything and winding
yourself up and then like it becomes
unsustainable and because again you're saying you're
and because again you're saying you're
trying to deny the presence of your
senses that are still seeing smelling
hearing tasting touching things that are
agreeable and disagreeable but you don't
see anything between so you're trying to
like get rid of the entire thing and
that so it always results in that
self-loathing that patiga that you know
those monks were contemplating the
the the
the body and the the kind of lost
perspective in the suttas that was
mentioned because you are trying to to to deny
because you are trying to to to deny
that which you don't need to and that's
why it's becoming unwholesome now
but uh i mean it's a summary you gave by
training an animal training a dog
you can't be strangling it yeah yeah
yeah you just have to train
you need to
take it pull it up pull it away
but actually you know that they think
that similar like you you have a cow
pull it away from eating in other
people's pastures
but you don't prevent indeed eating here
because if you don't let it eat here not
eat there well it's gonna die or try to
you know completely run away from you
so you lose your mind
yeah so it's like
so it's like
but it's important to take
responsibility for right away because
see like now you could think okay so i
must allow some agreeability thus i'm
justified he's like well you are
justified in agreeability but you're not
justified if you don't see the line
where agreeability is and where
sensuality is
so you can have things that are
agreeable that are not central
and you can't have central things that
are not agreeable so in other words
agreeability can exist without
sensuality sensuality requires agreeability so
sensuality requires agreeability so
essentiality is like a particular type
of agreeability
but if you actually
remove dependence on that particular
type that is provocative of lust and so
on you could just have agreeability of
seclusion of the senses and so on not be
dependent on it thus not fear not be
distraught you know when death or
sickness and so on come your way or if
no if disagreeable things come your way
that won't bother you either for example
academy imagine you're
you you're enclosed in a room with five
windows through which you perceive things
through which you perceive things
so you just see things as they come in
front of the windows
sometimes pleasing things sometimes
displeasing things and that's it you're
seated in a chair and you're just
registering things
yeah nose eyes
not not nothing else they're really like
in scene there's seen and so on but
if you don't see the difference between
the pleasure that is inducive of lust
that is trapping you that is hooking you
it is making for more that is causing
underlying tendency to crave for more
and so on
then when something agreeable of that
particular kind
say something that would provoke that
kind of
fever towards the sense object
feverish mind oh you wouldn't just be
sitting you're gonna get up you're gonna
lean through the window you're going to
try and get that thing closer you're
going to try and grab it fix it there
make it not go anywhere else stay within
your field of view possess it
and that's already completely so you
forgot all the other windows now
you're leaning out into this fear pretty
much that's that's not yours so the
point is like how much your mind moves
on account of things that are agreeable
and disagreeable how much you provoked
by it how much you have you cannot
resist that pressure and you give in and
you're just just crawling out of the
window trying to get that stuff
that's the danger of it
the beautiful things just remain in the
world as the buddha would say but it's
that fever that last that's why you are
subjected to the danger because you
expose yourself and counter it now
imagine you recognize that
so you're still seated there
and now you see when a thing comes into
the field of view through a window and
it's pressuring you to get up and go
back the old ways
and you realize oh that's the danger of
it so i don't do that so you restrain
and you refuse to look through the
window until that particular things go
go because you can't stay the whole time
now there is something agreeable there
that you can admire from your chair
your mind doesn't need to get up
you don't need to start acting out of
that pressure you just stay on the chair
oh look it's a beautiful sunset but i'm
not crawling out of the window or losing
perspective on everything else and then
that changes and you don't feel dejected
because it's changed because now it's
some horrible ugly sight of i don't know
rain bad weather cold i don't know what
it is but okay again my mind is not
moving from the chair
so regardless of the window you realize
that okay if i can see smell taste
perceive these five senses
without my mind moving flipping over
perturbing twisting run into words
i can sustain it
if there is a pressure a challenge
provoke to give in and start tumbling down
to give in and start tumbling down
basically you know through that momentum
of i gave in and now i can't stop oh
that's the danger
i don't do that
so when something comes to provoke to
hook you to bait you
that's okay nope
i refuse to look until it disappears
because it could result in this mind
getting up and running and tripping over
and falling out of the window and
meeting death or deadly suffering
but that doesn't mean oh because i get
hooked to these particular things that i
see i must block and board and destroy
all these windows and never see anything
again well
you are still you have to get off the
chair to block those windows but then
you have to get off the chair to chase
things away that are in front of the
windows but you realize but that was the
problem not what was in front of the
window that i could see the problem was
that i was getting up on account of it
the problem was that i wanted it so i
got up but i didn't want it so i got up
when the mind is completely completely
completely cooled down there is no basis
of passion even memories of passion to
provoke mind to get up from that chair
and you encounter things
that used to provoke lust or aversion
and now you realize that moving on
account of it is inconceivable because
the mind has been so tamed and that's
the it would have said that like oh yeah
when ananda asked him um so does the uh
a mind with that's enlightened do they
always live in the pleasure of
enlightenment or do they like calm down
and kind of go back to normal so to
speak so the pleasure comes down but
then when that mind would encounter
things that used to promote cluster
version destruction
he would experience that pleasure of
freedom because he would remind him of
the freedom
because you would obviously you would
know the significance the peril the
danger of each time even in the past you
got off the chair and tried to get you
know what provoked you or to get rid of
what provoked you
obviously fully understanding the danger
will then enable you to not give in and
get off the chair and it will then
eventually calm you down and then
because you haven't been feeding the
passion there will be no more passion
pressuring you so then you have these
things they used to provoke you
and you're absolutely motionless like
there is absolutely no movement in the
mind on account of it
with the memory of how much you used to
be controlled by that
and that's like oh wow look at the mind
is truly free
that's when when the monk would
recognize that but if and if there's
something there's something that's not
provoking you that's something that is
calm let's say
let's say
you realize that oh i can just eat
plain porridge
it doesn't make me more hungry i don't
crave it
i don't hate it either i don't hate to
exactly sustain myself if it goes
there's no problem yeah but yeah isn't
that wonderful
and that's wonderful isn't that
wonderful it's wonderful because it's extremely
it's wonderful because it's extremely
practical yeah and practicality is very
wonderful
because you don't worry about it simple
clothes very simple
serves the purpose uh
lightweight easy to patch and you don't
have to do anything in order to you know
procure it get it and nobody wants it
nobody else wants it so it's like oh
that's wonderful it's absolutely
burdenless absolutely easy
and that's that's pleasant and that's
not sensuality
generosity as well like that's why they
would to delay people before he would
teach him about the view he would like
elevate glad in their mind with talks on
generosity and rebirth and stuff as in
good pleasure
generosity is a good pleasure helping
others again even if you're not doing it for
again even if you're not doing it for
the purest of the reasons
still helping others being generous
giving it's actually a good type of
pleasure that is beneficial for the mind
because it's not the pleasure they will
provoke last first people's lives are
controlled by thirst by fever of their mind of
by thirst by fever of their mind of
rooted in lust rooted in a version
looted in distraction just an account of
yes those few particular
things that that provoke pleasure not
the entire eye domain and sites
just particular site sounds multi-status
yet that is the most important so
basically that becomes the criteria
for a mind that's dependent on that
sensual being
that becomes criteria for everything
else and even if they could see the pleasure
and even if they could see the pleasure
of seclusion the pleasure of generosity
until they see the danger of the other
type of pleasure that particular type of
central pleasure that is the pleasure
that controls the mind
everything else will be secondary to
that pleasure
so
yes it's it's it's a very kind of it's a
it's a narrow bait so to speak there is
more of a non-bait around there are more
things that are not beautiful in the
world than things that are beautiful
there are more ugly things than pretty
things generally non-provocative there
are exactly more things that are
non-provocative but if you haven't understood that the
but if you haven't understood that the
gratification the danger and the escape
in regard to the provocative things that
is your entire being kama baba is the
entire state of existence
on account of those few baits
few little hooks that you constantly
attached to
and they drag you left and right
and you see there is more of this but
because you're not developed in regard
to the these particular provocative
pleasures you are in their control so
you can't do anything about it until you
fully understand and free yourself from
that but yes the entire being needs to be
but yes the entire being needs to be
uprooted because that entire being
depends on getting off the chair to look
at that which is very pressuringly
beautiful getting off the chair to you know go and
getting off the chair to you know go and
shout at that which is very pressuringly
uh a verse
but you only do that you only get up
because you don't
see that as a danger yeah you don't see
getting up as a danger yeah you you're
fully immersed with with
that particular chord of central
pleasure so i can uh i can sit i can
force myself
to sit down i mustn't get up and that's
probably how you have to start sure you
took it on faith that you shouldn't get
up but i want to get up but you want to
get up but you are not getting up so
that's the first step that's the sense
restraint and because you're not getting up means
and because you're not getting up means
you are not acting out you're not you're
not sustaining the habit of getting up
so sooner or later if you keep keep
doing that you're going to start seeing
more in a sense of ah i haven't been
getting up effectually the aggregate of
virtue is there i haven't been breaking
the presets
i was very pressured to do so and
everything but i haven't been doing it
and there is already increasing
perspective yeah yeah
and then you you're already closer to
see like right so that was the problem
that was the trick that was the bait i
mean the bait
that was just to hook you
but the bait can't come through the
window and hook you out you are the one
who goes for it
and so what's the danger is the danger
that there are hooks around
or is the danger in the fact that you
can't stop grabbing them
oh but if only there were no hooks i
wouldn't be grabbing them well now
you're even avoiding responsibility for
grabbing the hooks
yes if there are only no mara and
samsara it would be great but there are
there is there are hooks there is some
sound of their essentiality so what is
the other thing that you could equally
do that would free you from it oh stop
reaching for the hooks
all right so i have to take
responsibility first for when i do reach
for the hooks and not blame the hooks
for my reaching
and then calm down and then stop
reaching and then see the freedom for
myself can i
can i
can i stop reach can i understand the
danger while while
while reaching
right can i understand the danger of
reaching for a hook
while at the same time are unable to
resist and stop reaching from a hook
well means the fact that you're reaching for
means the fact that you're reaching for
a cloak means you're not seeing the
danger
so that's the danger getting up
putting yourself there where then you
you will be
you will be in control of it not on the
way around
and if you think okay so if i can remain
in the chair and look at the things that
are provocative of lost and thirst
that's impossible
so it's impossible to have perceptions
of things
that are sensual pleasures
without perverting that order and
putting that first eye without getting
out of the chair
because the fact is again
you might not be getting out of the
chair but the view the sights
but the view the sights
the perceptions are pressuring you
and you don't see where the problem is
because you're still looking
if you realize where the problem is you
will automatically stop looking
ah right the problem is in the mind
they want to go there so why would i be
provoking this rabid dog that can harm
me
that i'm paired with instead of calming
it there is something provocative that
can result in you know ripping my arm
off when it when he charges for it
why would i even do that unless i don't
see the danger of a provoked dog which
is what my mind is
so that's when people think they can
engage with centrality mindfully
impossible means there's already no perspective if
means there's already no perspective if
you choose to engage even if it's to
that this i'll just let it look
i won't engage physically or verbally
but mentally unthinkable that's what i
said physically withdrawn
speech beautifully and mentally he does
not engage with he doesn't
accept welcome entertain thoughts of
sensuality because that would be the equivalent of
because that would be the equivalent of
being strapped to a rabid mad animal
that is calm
and then you show it things that are
making it even more rabid and mad
while you're strapped to it
so yeah i can hold it for now but the
point will come
and my grip will loosen or something and
then that animal will not remember me
it's going to just go wild people don't
realize that their mind has the mind of
its own
so your mind has a mind of its own
doesn't matter your sense of ownership
my mind my mind the truth is
that mind
it's basically on its own
i'm subjected to it
so that's the recognition of seeing the
sign of the mind as something that is
not yours that you are paired with
a chittender you have to mention
it's like being able to see the mind on
its own
and then okay so it's not really like no
but i should be able to look at this
without being pressured it's not up to
you the mind has a mind of of its own
that it sees these things it will go for
it if it doesn't see it will calm down
and that's now your wisdom
okay so i won't let it look through that
window until things clear out there oh
look now at some pleasant sights they
will calm me down yes look
because it's not then
feeling like completely you know
suffocating he can't look at anything
no no you can look at things that are
not provocative of lust aversion
distraction indolence
pressure to break the precepts all of
that and you you know that
it's it's very obvious what those things
are
but it takes that faith
just that first attempt to just
okay let me give it a go for a while
that restraint well yeah of course
none of this would make sense if a
person doesn't want to do it if a person
just is content with the view that everything
is content with the view that everything
is sensuality or nothing essentiality in
other words you can do whatever you want
or you shouldn't be doing anything
because everything is bad any type of
pleasure is bad any type of comfort's
bad any type of ability is bad
but then obviously
how about the thought that everything is
bad they don't find that to be a bad
thing because they're very much gripped
by it and fully
you know live their life under it yet
that thought is very agreeable to them
so you still you do accept agreeability
then which contradicts your own view
that any agreeability should not be
accepted so why are you then accepting
the agreeability of the view that any
agreeability should not be accepted that
surely must be agreeable to you
otherwise you will not be able to hold
that view
so it's a contradiction in terms
sensuality is a contradiction in terms
denial of sensuality denial of debate
shunning everything is also
contradiction same saying yes to
everything or saying no to everything
except saying no terry so seeing the
middle way it's is the way out so
learning what debate is learning what
the five chords of central pleasure is
it's not all sight sounds melted touches
what is the five
feverish exactly it's those that are provocative
exactly it's those that are provocative
of lust provocative aversion provocative
of lost perspective it's the you feel
that pressure you feel that impulse
okay that's why this is unwholesome not
because of this or that so do you start
seeing where the problem is
so that's again pleasure of seclusion
pleasure of remote dwellings pleasure
renunciation like pleasure of simple life
like pleasure of simple life
pleasure of non-distraction
although the pressure stills they come
through site sounds male test touches i
mean how would you have a pleasure of
seclusion unless you're perceiving this
beautifully secluded forestry of other
people you are seeing things and that's exactly
you are seeing things and that's exactly
why people would confuse they would
think oh well that sensuality as well
because they would think that any
pleasure that comes through eyes means
sensuality no if there is no pressure if there is
no if there is no pressure if there is
no love if there is no loss of
perspective and lust
that is that pleasure you don't need to
fear because you are not losing
perspective in regard to it
and that's how you can disown it in
order to disown it you need to first
stop resisting it or stop indulging it
you need to stop getting out of the
chair so you need to calm your mind and then
so you need to calm your mind and then
recognize that okay this agreeable
pleasure has been
now for a while replacing
my need for the you know
provocative pleasures
i haven't been engaging with sensuality
because i've been developing pleasure of
seclusion and my mind has come down as a
result of it
my mind is not getting out of the chair
not trying to to leap out of the window
and now within that you can disown that
wholesome pleasure
not get rid of it
oh i must go to the city in order to
disown the pleasure of seclusion no no
no
while you're in the pleasure of
seclusion you actually get to see that
it's the senses pleasure and you have
nothing to do with it and you don't
depend on it you don't need it and you
can see all those things because there's
no lust underlying it
and you can't see all those things in
regard to the five chords of sensual
pleasure because there is lust
underlying it
there is lust constricting the
perspective there is a version constricting the
there is a version constricting the
perspective of distraction
and that's exactly the pleasure of jhana
and well the pleasure that you get
before jhana which is which is what
would have said oh
why am i feeling these pleasures have
nothing to do with five codes of central
pleasure what if i let him be he let
them be the mind became very peaceful
very pliable the dog became very
obedient because you stopped choking it
and now you are the one so no you don't
look at that because that will provoke
you you can look at this because that
will calm you down
you don't go there because they will
induce more you go over there because
they will reduce more
make things clear and becomes clearer
for you then basically what mind is what
mind owns and that's how you free
yourself from it
from any ownership any misconceiving of
ownership and so on
yeah yeah protecting
the senses guarding the senses
protecting the senses not that restraint
does maybe sound he has to start with
restraint because as i said
although you can think this
theoretically everybody starts by
already being dependent on on the on
that five codes of central pleasure so
everybody starts with that proliferated
sensuality in other words sensuality is first
in other words sensuality is first
agreeable things that are sometimes
sensual or something essential sometimes
not they don't see that everything is
basically seen central because that's
the framework of the view the dependence
so the sensory strength and withdrawal
needs to come first but then yes once
you recognize start seeing the signs of
your own mind seated in the chair
start seeing the choices to make whether
you want to leap out of the window or
restrain that already becomes on the level of
that already becomes on the level of
guarding the senses
like i guard it
so it means i only act when necessary oh
no come back but gardening does not mean
i'm just constantly holding it in a
chokehold or something yeah protecting
you just kind of oh don't look at that
don't go too far come here but allowing
it to move about
and that's how then you get to learn
about that mind
because you're not letting it run free
when you can't see anything because you
just dragged around with it
and you're not trying to kill it either
by preventing it to be alive basically
and then you get to see
mind has a life
of its own
eyes have a life of its own
so in scene there's just the scene in
heard in thought it's just a thought
none of that's mine none of that is
misconceived is mine none of that is
owned and then that's it and mine's free then
and then that's it and mine's free then
those things they use to provoke lust
and those habits of that becomes even
more inconceivable
but in order to reach that state
basically you need to find pleasures
that are not of the provocative kind
pleasure seclusion pleasure
pronunciation and so on